Finding Aid for Edward C. Crafts papers, 1951-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward C. Crafts papers 1951-1975
Crafts, Edward C. (Edward Clayton), 1910-
13 linear feet
85115 Aa 2
Conservation consultant, U. S. Forest Service administration, director of Bureau of Outdoor Recreation, U. S. Department of the Interior. Oral histories, speeches and publications, legislative files, consultation materials, and other professional papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Edward Crafts (donor no. 5730 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward Clayton Crafts was born in Chicago, April 14, 1910. In 1931, following his graduation from the University of Michigan, Crafts went west as a forester with the Intermountain Forest and Range Experimental Station in Ogden, Utah. From 1932 to 1940, he was with the Southwestern Forest and Range Experimental Station in Tucson; and from 1940 to 1944, he was with the California Forest and Range Experimental Station in Berkeley. From 1944 to 1950, Crafts was Chief of the Division of Forest Economics with the Forest Service of the U.S. Dept. Agriculture. He then became Assistant Chief of the U.S. Forest Service serving from 1950 to 1962. From 1962 to 1969, he was director of the newly established Bureau of Outdoor Recreation with the Interior Dept. Thereafter, he worked as a conservation consultant. He died in 1980.
The Edward Crafts collection documents his varied career as a consultant, and as an expert on federal forestry and conservation issues. Much of the files relate to federal legislation, mainly from the period when he was with the Bureau of Outdoor Recreation. Other files concern various forestry topics, some from his years with the U.S. Forest Service.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Forests and forestry--United States.; United States. Bureau of Outdoor Recreation.; United States. Forest Service.
- Biographical / Personal
  - Oral history 1969 (Lyndon Johnson Library) (Box 1)
  - Oral history 1972 "Forest Service Researcher and Congressional Liaison: An Eye to Multiple Use" (Forest History Society) (Box 1)
  - Oral history 1975 "Congress and the Forest Service, 1950-1962" (University of California, Bancroft Library) (Box 1)
    (Need permission of Bancroft Library and E.C. Crafts before publishing)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Cosmos Club membership file (Box 1)
    (include biographical material)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
  - Publications, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches (Box 1)
  - Speeches prepared by E.C. Crafts (delivered by others) (Box 1)
  - Personal papers 1951-1968 (Box 1)
- Legislation
  - Multiple Use and Sustained Yield Act 1960 (Box 2)
    (include legislative materials and related background files)
  - Wild Rivers System legislation 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Scenic Rivers System legislation 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut River legislation 1966 (Box 2)
  - Land and Water Conservation Fund Act (and amendments) 1965-1970 (Box 3)
  - Entrance, Admission, and User Fees legislation 1966 (Box 4)
    (include legislative materials and related background files; some materials on Golden Eagle Passport program, 1969-1971)
  - Proposed Department of Natural Resources 1967-1974 (Box 4)
    (include position papers and related materials largely concerning effect of legislation on Forest Service)
  - Proposed transfer of Forest Service from Department of Agriculture to Department of Interior circa 1935-1959 (Box 4)
  - Redwood National Park bill 1967 (Box 5)
  - North Cascades National Park bill 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Uniform Federal Grazing Land Act 1953 (Box 7)
  - Public Land Grazing Fees 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - High Timber Yield Fund legislation 1969 (Box 7)
  - Public Land Policy legislation 1971 (Box 7)
- Bureau of Outdoor Recreation and related
  - "Promise and Choice -- The Nationwide Outdoor Recreation Plan" 1969 (Box 8)
  - "Promise and Choice -- The Nationwide Outdoor Recreation Plan" 1969 (cont.) (Box 9)
  - National Water Commission 1972-1973 (Box 9)
  - Report on water-based recreation on federal lands (Box 9)
    (background files and related materials)
  - History of Park, Parkways Recreational Areas Act June 23, 1936 (Box 10)
  - Memos to Secretary of Interior from E.C. Crafts 1967-1968 (Box 10)
  - Briefing materials 1969 from Bureau of Outdoor Recreation (E.C. Crafts) to new Secretary of Interior (Hickel) (Box 10)
  - President's Council and Citizens Advisory Committee on Recreation and Natural Beauty 1967-1969 (Box 10)
  - Citizens Committee on Natural Resources 1973-1974 (Box 10)
  - Puerto Rico consultation work 1969-1970 Natural Resources Subcommittee, Governor's Advisory Council-for the Development of Government Programs (Box 10)
- Forest Service Topical Files
  - Shared Revenues (Box 10)
  - Recreation (Box 10)
  - Long-range planning (Box 11)
  - Policy statements (Box 11)
  - Forest and recreation research (Box 11)
  - Controversy between Departments of Interior and Agriculture over proposed land transfers 1958-1967 (Box 11)
  - National Forest Recreation Survey (work Plan) 1959 (Box 11)
  - Environmental Program for the Future 1973 (Box 11)
  - National Forest Areas (Box 11)
- Other topics
  - Management of Public Lands hearings 1971 and Public Land Policy legislation, 1971 (Box 11)
  - Clear-cutting hearings and legislation 1970-1971 (Box 11)
  - Clear-cutting hearings and legislation 1970-1971 (Box 12)
  - Society of American Foresters, Little Rock meeting 1972 (Box 12)
    (largely concerning clear-cutting issue)
  - Corps of Engineers, Recreation Management Task Force 1968 (Box 12)
    (draft report)
  - Range appraisal, Grazing Service 1944 (Box 12)
  - Forest Service retirees group. Correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 12)
  - National Forest Land reforestation legislation 1972 (Box 12)
  - National Forest Management legislation 1973 (Box 12)
  - National Wilderness Preservation System legislation 1973 (Box 12)
  - Leasing of Federal Timber lands for recreational purposes legislation 1973 (Box 12)
  - Task Force on Resources and Recreation 1966 (Box 12)
  - Nation-wide Trails System hearings and legislation 1967 (Box 12)
  - Federal Water Project Recreation, Act 1969 (Box 13)
  - Enforcement of laws by Department of Interior (legislative files) 1970 (Box 13)
  - Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument (Box 13)
  - Bureau of Outdoor Recreation
    - Fee Study (Box 13)
    - Index of legislation affecting B.O.R. 1961-1969 (Box 13)
  - Water Resources Council (Box 13)
  - Boy Scouts of America activities (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Printed material (Box 13)